<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A visitation speech delivered at Colchester in Essex, 1662</title>
            <author>Hansley, John, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23912</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12581196</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199259</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240988941</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H662</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12581196</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 324:1p or 2091:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A visitation speech delivered at Colchester in Essex, 1662</title>
                  <author>Hansley, John, d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Colchester.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Hansley. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Sixteenth title in a filmed collection of visitation articles.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199259:1"/>
            <p>A Visitation Speech DELIVERED AT COLCHESTER IN ESSEX. 1662.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:199259:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199259:2"/>
            <p>WHen I consider that Miracle of Mercies these three dying Kingdoms now so suddenly, so strangely, restored to health; when I look upon the late Changes in this Nation, so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably, so unexpected, so stupendious, from what we were of late, to what we are now: I think I may very fitly, by way of Allusion, call these times, as S. <hi>PETER</hi> calls those other times, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The times of Restitution,</hi> or the times of restoring all things; For have we not seen Monarchy restored, Our gracious Soveraign restored, Our Parliaments restored, the Militia restored, Our Church restored, Our Bishops restored, Our Laws and Judges restored, Our Liberty restored, Our Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical Courts restored, and our selves restored to our selves again?</p>
            <p>With what bleeding hearts did we formerly behold these three Kingdoms, like a Body without a Head, in horrible confusion under those many monstrous sorts of Government, Democracy, Aristocracy, Stratocracy, Oligarchy, Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: Nay, what a monstrous body was that (pardon the expression) when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little bone in the <hi>Rump</hi> was swelled as big as a Head: How was that Fathers Censure of this Island then made good, (S. <hi>HIEROM</hi>) <hi>Brittannia tyranno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum provincia fertilissima?</hi> How were we rid, and whipt, and spurd by all sorts of those cruel Masters? But blessed be God that we have seen <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that best form of Government, which seemed to have been put to Death with that blessed <hi>Martyr,</hi> again revived: Our <hi>floating</hi> Island now setled upon its Old Basis, and that from Parity and Anarchy, as weary of that Calf, we are resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Order and Monarchy. <hi>Monarchy</hi> the best curb to emulations and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, the best fence against animosities and ambitions, the best support of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans interest, the best remedy against confusion, and the best means of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing our peace and happiness: What else speaks one God in the World, one Sun in Heaven, one Soul in Man, one Heart in the Body, but one King in a Kingdom, to be the most absolute, most free, most happy form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And to this happiness and freedom hath God now restored us, under the government of our Lawful Hereditary Soveraign King.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199259:3"/>
            <p>A KING whose Education abroad, hath fitted him for his Government at home, who hath no more suffered in all his tribulations, then the Sun in an Eclipse, which onely hath served to make him the more resplendent, whom though God suffered for a while to be as a wandring Star, yet now to our great joy we see him fixed in the Orbe of his own Dominions, and guilding this British World with his matchless Lustre, and long may his sweet Influences, be the source of all our Felicities. Nor do we see him restored onely to his <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Revenews,</hi> but to all other his <hi>Native</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> Rights: One of the chief of which is his power over the MILITIA, signified by the sword put into his hand at the Coronation; without which, A Monarch is a <hi>King and no King;</hi> without which, disaffected persons would look upon him as the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listins</hi> did upon <hi>Sampson,</hi> without his hair, in which his strength lay: but blessed be God, that that withered hand is now restored which will not bear the sword in vain.</p>
            <p>Nor may this time be called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a time of restoring,</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in respect of his Majesty; but likewise in divers other relations, as the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man sayes of wisdom, <hi>Omnia mihi bona pariter venere cum illa,</hi> All good things came to me along with her; so many other restorings came along with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing of our Gracious Soveraign; as, first the restoring of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>We have seen PARLIAMENTS restored again to their former privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and splendour, and filled again with the three estates, Lords Spiritual, Lords Temporal, and Commons, which like a threefold cord cannot easily be broken; to whom his Majesty ascribes so much, that he esteems them as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to his Greatness, as leaves about the rose to preserve its beauty: And though one of those Estates then devoured the other two, and most unnaturally some of her own Members; yet now we see the <hi>Coronets</hi> flourishing with the <hi>Crown,</hi> and <hi>Peerage</hi> acting again in its former sphere, and the two Houses re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished again with men of science and conscience, the two sources of as many signal blessings to this Church and Kingdom, as all former Chronicles since the Conquest have recorded: so that well may this time in reference to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament be called a time of restoring; I, and well may this Parliament be stiled the <hi>Restoring Parliament,</hi> the <hi>repairer of our breaches, and the restorer of pathes to dwell in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a time of restoring too, we must needs call it, if we look upon the CHURCH, and <hi>state Ecclesiastical:</hi> How did we despair of ever seeing that flourish again, when it was stubb'd up root and branch? But now we have seen <hi>Aarons</hi> rod budding and blossoming again; Now we see our Our Churches resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which formerly were dens of Thieves, and stables for Horses; and our Churchmen restored, who were formerly outed by seditious bold intruders, and instead of ringing, <hi>Curse ye Meroz</hi> in every Pulpit, we have now <hi>Aarons</hi> Bells
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199259:3"/>striking on both sides, <hi>Fear God, honour the King:</hi> And instead of a dry empty Directory, which had neither the <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> nor <hi>Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> in room of that <hi>Talmud sabaudicum,</hi> the Savoyan Talmud, as <hi>Ramus</hi> call'd the platform of <hi>Geneva</hi> Discipline; we have the ancient Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> saith, was <hi>made by the aid of the Holy Ghost;</hi> and of which, the worst that <hi>Calvin</hi> could say, was, that there were in it <hi>Ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiae quaedam tollerabiles;</hi> though he was pleased to call them <hi>Ineptiae,</hi> things not to fit and proper as he supposed, yet even in his esteem, they were <hi>tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles.</hi> And as the fountain of all these</p>
            <p>We have seen to our great rejoyceing, Our reverend BISHOPS restored to their former <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Jurisdictions;</hi> and not such Bishops as were some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time emblem'd by a smooth Ash, that does nothing but bear keyes, but such as <hi>Erasmus</hi> once spoke of, <hi>Sola Anglia doctos habet Episcopos;</hi> such as Bishop <hi>James Mountagues</hi> commendation of Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erkins</hi> in his funeral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermon, may very well sute with, that teach <hi>England</hi> to <hi>serve God,</hi> and Ministers to <hi>preach Jesus Christ;</hi> and it is his Majesties great care, that it may never be said of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Prelates, as of <hi>Saul,</hi> that when he came to the High places, he made an end of prophesying.</p>
            <p>And a time of Restoring too we must needs acknowledg it, if we look upon our Brethren of the Gown, that noble and worthy Profession of the LAW: How sad was the face of things when we were governed by an Arbitrary Power; when most matters were determined by men of lost conscience, and reputation; <hi>Remota Justitia;</hi> What were our Kingdoms but <hi>Magna Latrocinia,</hi> great Thievedoms? That Emblem of <hi>Alciat</hi> did very well suit with those times; <hi>Piscerculos aurata rapit medio aequore Sardas.</hi> The silly Sprats being under the water are chased up and down by the great Guilt-heads, and if they spring out of the Sea for fear, they are quickly devoured of the gready Seamewes. Thus were the poorer people hunted and pursued by the great Guiltheads their rich neighbours; and if they sought to be relieved by the Law, they were sure to fall into the hands of some mercenary <hi>Demosthenes;</hi> and so were in the poor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans case in the Gospel, who after she had spent all that she had, was nothing the <hi>better,</hi> but much the <hi>worse.</hi> But now God hath restored our <hi>Judges as at first, and our Counsellours as at the beginning:</hi> Now we see the seats of Justice filled with men of Integrity and Conscience, who account it their honour to be the guardians of liberty, and property, the rescuers of poor men from invasion and oppression; and to use the Psalmists words, <hi>who keep the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple folk by their right, and deliver their souls from oppression and wrong.</hi> And may these two Gowned Nations, the <hi>Clergy</hi> and the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> now at last learn wisdom by their sufferings; and seeing their difference have rendred them a prey to the common adversary, may they henceforth lay aside all animosities, and mutually support one another, and both together, like <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> support our MOSES.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199259:4"/>
            <p>And one thing more we cannot forget, the print of our shackles puts us in mind of it, to make it a time of restoring too in regard of our <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>freedom</hi> from our former <hi>slavery.</hi> How did we groan under the cruel usage of those tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Usurpers, by whom we were not so much governed as destroyed? by whom we were not sufferd so much liberty as to grieve for our slavery, but were dealt withal as theives deal with them they rob, bound and gagg'd, that we might neither stir to help our selves, nor cry out for the help of others. But blessed be God, who <hi>remembred us in our low estate,</hi> and by the valour and prudence of a renowned GENERAL restored us to our lost liberty; Of which, as we have a high share, so let us have a deep sence, never forgetting those blessings with which God hath crowned his undertakings, but ever acknowledging the settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our state both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> to be ascribed, next under God, to that <hi>unparallell'd Instrument.</hi> And may it be th' vote of all true English hearts, that that noble Duke, <hi>qui nobis hac otia fecit,</hi> may for ever be the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling both of Prince and people. But as for those discontented spirits, whose fingers yet itch to be ringing the changes, may the ropes so gall them, as may make them at last beshrew their own fingers.</p>
            <p>And we cannot for shame but take in our own COURTS here, and make it a time of Restoring for them too: O how was the poor Clergy stung by swarmes of Committee-men in every Town, City, and County: <hi>Committee-men</hi> a greater pest to the Gentry and Clergy of this Land, than ever was the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to the Moores in <hi>Spain.</hi> Men that professed Divinity, but never shewed the least humanity. Men that cried down all forms, but a <hi>form of godliness,</hi> which onely they had, and <hi>denied the power thereof.</hi> Men that used the Word of God, as some say of <hi>Benedicts</hi> Rule, onely to <hi>profess,</hi> but not to <hi>perform.</hi> Men that pretended to serve God, when they intended to serve themselves of him. Men that made much ado about setting Christ upon his Throne, but it was that they might be his Deputies. Men that would have been thought An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, though it were but for troubling the water, that they might have the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fishing. Men that tore the Churches garments, to make their own whole; and pull'd down the wall of <hi>Sion,</hi> to build their <hi>Babel:</hi> and, to borrow the words of that Right Reverend and Learned Bishop in his Coronation Sermon, <hi>Men that sacrificed the publick Interest to their particular concernments, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the whole Nation to fight against it self, and to cut one anothers throats, to gratifie their malice and ambition.</hi> Men that imbroyled all to enrich themselves, and set other mens houses on fire, that by the help of the light they might see the better to run away with the goods. Men that had neither conscience to awe them, nor shame to restrain them from doing any thing; Every thing that might speak shame or sorrow to the Gentry and the Clergy. These were then our Taskmasters, who had usurped upon the managing of these <hi>Courts,</hi> and to these were we to render the tale of our Brick, whose meaness and baseness, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199259:4"/>many places was such, that it added much to the pressures of our slavery; for, <hi>Asperius nihil est humili cum surgit in altum;</hi> and flies bred from the dunghill, they say, have the sharpest sting. O how was <hi>Aarons Rod</hi> most miserably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured and swallowed up by these Committee-mens <hi>Ox-goads</hi> and <hi>Cartwhips!</hi> How were our <hi>Lamps snuffed,</hi> not by the golden snuffers of the Sanctuary, but by <hi>Demetrius the Silver-smith,</hi> and <hi>Alexander the Copper-smith,</hi> and men of such mettal? How was the Ark of the Church, which was wont to be carried by <hi>Levites,</hi> now carried by these <hi>beasts</hi> of the uncircumcised Philistins, shaken, and tottered, and overturned? How did these Churches Vergers sweep our Church, not with the <hi>besome of Reformation,</hi> as they pretended, but with the <hi>besome of destruction?</hi> Such like sweepers as the Romish Vulgar makes the woman in the Gospel to be, which in stead of <hi>domum everrit,</hi> reads <hi>domum ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit;</hi> who in stead of sweeping it, turned it upside down, and cast, not only the Clergy out of the Church, but the Church out of the windows! O how were our souls filled with the scornful reproofs of the wealthy, and with the despite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness of the proud! But blessed be God who hath taken down our <hi>harps from the willows,</hi> hath brought our Courts into their former current, restor'd our Jurisdiction to its pristine beauty, and turn'd our captivity from under Committee men, into the milde and sweet government of <hi>Episcopal jurisdiction!</hi> And let our submission to their Laws and Censures never seem irksom, or burdensom to us, seeing the want of the due execution of these was the main cause of all our miseries; for had those Currs been muzled by Ecclesiastical censures, they had never by their bauling so disturbed our peace and quiet: But <hi>Eli</hi> begat <hi>Phineas,</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> begat <hi>Ichabod;</hi> remissness in Governours, begat prophane and seditious Priests, and these begat <hi>Ichabod,</hi> shame and ruine, and confusion to our Church and Kingdom. And thus you see that in all these respects we may very fitly call these times, as S. <hi>PETER</hi> calls those other times, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the times of restitution,</hi> or the times of restoring all things.</p>
            <p>ANd now since God hath done so much for us, let us not be wanting to our selves, but do what we can on our own parts, to make it a time of <hi>restoring</hi> too.</p>
            <p>And in the first place, Let us make it a time of restoring for the <hi>reading</hi> of the COMMON PRAYER BOOK in our Churches. S. <hi>John</hi> wept when there was not one found to <hi>open</hi> the Book: And what a lamentable thing is it, that many should be so peevish as not to open <hi>this</hi> Book; the very reading of which, caused our forefathers the Martyrs to weep for joy. But I need not press this upon you; you'l say, you do read it: I, but how readest thou? You read it as <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> did <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> roll, three or four leaves of it, and then cast it away: Nor will your pretence of infirmity of body, or shortness of breath serve
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199259:5"/>for an excuse; for how then come you to be such long winded Preachers? How is it that you can bestow three or four hours in eager and violent discourse to justifie your inability, when as the third part of that breath sufficiently testifies your ability: But the truth is, you want cordialness, and not cordials; and a heart to it, rather then pectorals. The <hi>Athenians</hi> banished <hi>Terpander,</hi> for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one string to his Harp; what then do you deserve who have taken away so many, that you have quite marred the Churches Musick, and have turned all into jarrs and discords? For by this mangling and curtailing of the <hi>Common-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> as your selves please, what do you else but make your selves Bishops in your own Parishes? You revive that Puritan Tenet, <hi>That nothing must be injoyned, but all left to your own liberty;</hi> You call in question the wisdome of the State; you flatly disobey an Act of Parliament; you bring the Common Prayer into disgrace and dislike with the people, as a frivolous, unnecessary, super fluous piece of service, and so bid fair for the ushering in that <hi>Goddess</hi> of the Presbyterians, the <hi>Directory,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant.</hi> When the daily Sacrifice was taken away, then was set up the abomination of desolation; and when this daily Sacrifice, the Prayers and Service of our Church shall be suffered to be thus scorned, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed and abused; we may well fear that abomination of Desolation to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced and set up again amongst us: Nor would I have you scrupulous to read it, as you are injoyned, in your <hi>Surplice</hi> and Formalities; though <hi>Michol</hi> scorned the <hi>linnen Ephod,</hi> yet <hi>David</hi> did not leave it off for all that. The Text says, <hi>That Michol was barren;</hi> I wonder how she comes to have so many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren amongst us, that scorn the Holy habit and Exercises? but however your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution must be that of <hi>Davids, I will still do it, It is before the Lord who hath chosen me before all thy fathers house.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANd secondly, Let us make it a time of restoring too for CATECHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SING in our Churches. <hi>Julian</hi> the Apostate, that subtile enemy of the Church, that he might the more easily root out Religion, suppressed all Christian Schools and places of Catechizing as the onely way to do it; and since this <hi>exercise</hi> of Catechising hath been neglected amongst us, how hath our Kingdom been overspread with ignorance, violence, perjuries, murthers, Sects, Heresies, Seditions, Rebellions, and all kinds of mischief that can bee named or thought on. In <hi>Proverbs</hi> 22.6. <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, <hi>Train up a child, Gnal pi darcho, secundum os viae,</hi> according to his capacity, according to the mouth of his way; a Metaphor taken from narrow-mouth'd vessels, which must have water often, and by little and little poured into them; so to those who have narrow and weak apprehensions, <hi>Precept must be upon precept, precept upon precept, line upon line, line upon line, here a little and there a little,</hi> as it is, <hi>Isai.</hi> 28.10.</p>
            <p>This the word <hi>Catechism</hi> intimates (which signifies, the <hi>repetition of the same
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199259:5"/>sound</hi>) that the office of the Catechist is to go often over with the same thing; to which agrees that word which is used <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Thou shalt teach these words unto thy Children;</hi> or, thou shalt whet or sharpen thy children with them. <hi>Shenanti.</hi> As the knife goes often over the whetstone before it be sharpened, so these words must be often repeated, till the people have made them their own. In <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.14. it is said of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that <hi>he armed his trained servants, Hhanican,</hi> his catechised and initiated servants, not onely trained in the discipline of War, but also catechised in the Principles of Religion. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.5. it is said, <hi>That Abraham took Sarah, and Lot, and all the souls which they had gotten in Haran;</hi> it is in the Hebrew, which they had made, <hi>Gnashu;</hi> and so <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynsworth</hi> reads it; they had not onely gotten them into their possession and service, but also had won them to the faith of God; or as the <hi>Caldee paraphrase</hi> hath it, had <hi>subdued them to the Law;</hi> and the Hebrews say, that <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>teach the men,</hi> and <hi>Sarah the women: Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> made souls, made them new by instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and catechising them. After <hi>Abraham</hi> we have <hi>David</hi> saying, Psal. 34. <hi>Come ye children hearken unto me, I will teach you the fear of the Lord;</hi> that is, the first Principles; for the <hi>fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom:</hi> and that Psalm is composed according to the order of the Hebrew Alphabet, the verses of it beginning with the letters thereof, in their vulgar and usual order, that so children and learners, together with the first elements of other learning, might have an alphabet of piety and godliness taught them; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> sets it down as a thing well known, and as one of the priviledges of the Jewes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17. that he was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>catechised out of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the new Testament we have our Saviour catechising of his Disciples, <hi>Whom do you say that I am?</hi> and <hi>Simon Peter</hi> answering the question, in the name of the rest, <hi>Thou art Christ the Son of God the living;</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.41. we have him catechising the Pharisees, He asked them, saying, <hi>What think ye of Christ, whose son is he?</hi> they say unto him, <hi>the Son of David;</hi> then he propounds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother question unto them, <hi>How can he be both the Son of David, and the Lord of David, for David calls him Lord?</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> writes to <hi>Theophilus</hi> a large Declaration of those things wherein he had formerly been catechised <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.4. <hi>Apollos</hi> was <hi>catechised</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the way of the Lord,</hi> Acts 18.25. and saith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 6.6. <hi>Let him that is taught in the words, communicate to him that teacheth in all good things,</hi> so we render it, but in the Greek it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And in the first chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the Apostle sets down the chief points of the Catechism then used: After the Apostles, the first we have <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangelist catechist at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and after him <hi>Pantenus, Clemens, Origen,</hi> who (such was either the necessity of the times, or the abilities of the man) at 18 years of age, took upon him that office, and was eminent in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Canisius</hi> the Jesuite will tell us more in those times; saith he, <hi>Nos hoc
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199259:6"/>munus suscipimus,</hi> we Jesuites make catechising our profession; This they glory in, that they are catechizers; and in that profession, saith he, we have S. <hi>Basil,</hi> S. <hi>Austine,</hi> St. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> in our society; and truly as Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizers they have, and in the conclusion of his Epistle to his Catechism, he saith, If nothing else, yet this alone should provoke us to greater diligence in Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chising, the <hi>Improbus labor,</hi> and <hi>Indefessa cura</hi> of the Protestants in this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise: So it was then, and upon the Protestants diligence this way, was occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned that order of <hi>Trent, that upon Sundayes and Holy dayes they should preach in the forenoon, and catechise in the afternoon.</hi> And let the <hi>Improbus labor</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defessa cura,</hi> of the Jesuits provoke us now at last, to restore again that exercise. Let us bow and stoop to the meanest capacity, <hi>That the simple one may receive wisdom, and the young man knowledg and discretion.</hi> Because we must give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the souls that are under us, therefore it behoves us with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to chuse rather to <hi>speak five words with understnnding,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 Cor. 14.19. <hi>then ten thousand otherwise.</hi> As <hi>Rabsekah</hi> said in another case to <hi>Eliakim, Hezekias</hi> Messenger, <hi>Am I sent to thy Master and thee, onely to speak these words, and not to the people also that are on the wall?</hi> So you are not sent onely to two or three Intellectualists in a Congregation, but to all the Lords people be they never so mean, never so ignorant. It is meeter that they which know, should be wearied with often repetitions, then that they that are unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full should be sent away empty for want of instruction; nay men, you know, may be nourished with milk, though infants cannot live with stronger meat; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven they who think themselves some body, may have somewhat in these Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to chew upon. <hi>Except ye become as little children ye shall not enter into the Kingdom of heaven;</hi> Except, ye the people, be content at first to feed on the milk of the word, and not presently fall to gnawing of bones of Controversies, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revealed Misteries; and except you the Ministers descend and apply your selves to the capacity of little children, and become as they, you lose your own way, you stop theirs to the Kingdom of Heaven: <hi>Except you become as little children you shall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. Jacob</hi> had a care that the tender flocks might not be over-driven, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.13. And it is the care and the charge too (Let me acquaint you with that) of our Right Reverend, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant, and tender Diocesan, that young Christians that are not able to hold pace, or go along with others, be not left behind; but be led on <hi>Jacobs</hi> pace, led on softly as they are able to endure, till you have brought them into the fold of Christ: and for this purpose you <hi>are enjoyned</hi> to turn your after noon Sermons into an exposition and explanation of the Church Catechism.</p>
            <p>And when we have made it a time for the restoring of Catechising; then in the next Place and Order, we may make it a time for the restoring of the LORDS SUPPER: An Office so strangely vanished out of our Churches, as that we may as well be taken for Jewes, or Turks, or Quakers, as for Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199259:6"/>having cast off that Badge and Cognizance of our Religion. It goes against your Conscience some of you to say, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, Christ have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us.</hi> I, but it goes not against your Conscience to with-hold from your people the precious body and blood of Christ, to keep them from their pardon, from hell, and their assurance of heaven, to debar them of the life of their souls, and all the sweet fruits and comforts of that Holy Sacrament: Sure if it were but for this one thing, your whole lives exercise ought to be nothing else but the repetition of these Petitions, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, Christ have mercy upon us;</hi> You should put up all your <hi>suits</hi> in the Court of Requests in no other form but this of mercy; you should send this word as a winged Messenger every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Throne of Grace; mercy should be both the Introduction, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and close of all our prayers, and no words or accents should be heard from you but these Obtestations and Obsecrations, and importunate intreaties of <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, Christ have mercy upon us,</hi> and all too little to expiate this horrid impiety. Alas, how will you answer it either to God or your own selves, to have required from your people their dues, when you have not done your duty? with what face have you eaten the bread of their Tables, and have denied them the bread of the Lords Table? How could you drink wine in bouls upon the sweat of their labours, and yet with-hold from them the wine of the Sacrament, which cost you no labour? With what Conscience could you thus fat up your own bodies, and thus starve your peoples souls? and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their temporals, when you have not made them partakers of your spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als? <hi>I have compassion on the multitude, for they have now stayed with me three days and have nothing to eat, give ye them to eat, least they faint by the way.</hi> But your people have stayed with you, and hung upon you, not three days, but three years; nay, thrice three years and upward, and yet you never set before them any of this heavenly food to keep their souls from fainting. Where are your bowels? what is become of your compassions? Have you cast off all humanity? Was the fear of God, the love of your neighbours, and the care of your own souls utterly abandoned? O horrible impiety! O monstrous cruelty! Nay, worse then monstrous! for even the <hi>Sea-monsters draw out their breasts, they give suck to their yong ones, but the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the Ostridge in the Wilderness: The tongue of the child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst, the children ask bread, and no man breaks it unto them.</hi> Well fare that late bloody Tyrant in this particular, that when he was resolved to murther our late gracious Soveraign, yet he had this care of his soul, not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him the ghostly comfort of this blessed Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcus</hi> the Emperour going through <hi>Palestine</hi> towards <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and observing the tumultuousness of the Jews, cryed out, <hi>O Marcomanni! O Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di! O Sarmatae! tandem vobis inquietiores inveni:</hi> And in like manner may we cry out, O ye Anabaptists, and Katabaptists! O ye Ranters and Seekers! O ye
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199259:7"/>Familists and Quakers! I have found now men and that amongst the Clergy, more bloudy, more inhumane, more cruel then the most barbarous wretch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst that cursed crue of Phanaticks! O ye merciless hard-hearted Nurses, thus to starve sorded poor creatures committed to your charge, especially since you were so well paid for their nursing. Before the Israelites were to enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> they were to eat the Passeover, <hi>Josh.</hi> 5.10. As ever you hope, you or your people, to enter into the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> you must be receivers of the blessed Sacrament; for they who will not <hi>drink</hi> the <hi>Cup of blessing,</hi> shall <hi>drink</hi> the <hi>Cup of trembling;</hi> and they who <hi>refuse</hi> the Supper of the Lord, shall be for ever <hi>kept</hi> from the Supper of the Lamb.</p>
            <p>But receiving is not sufficient, if carriage be not Christian. Better be absent than rudely present; for thats but a neglect of God, this a scorn of him. I shall therefore in the next place put you in mind of making this time a time of restoring too, in respect of due <hi>reverence</hi> in GODS HOUSE and SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VICE. That the Patriarchs had set houses and places of Gods Worship, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not onely by the set Altars and Groves; but by the speech of <hi>Jacob, This place is no other than the House of God, and the gate of Heaven.</hi> If there had not been set Houses, <hi>Jacob</hi> would not have compared this place to the House of God; neither would he have dedicated it by erecting a Statue and pouring oyl, had there not been solemn dedications of such Houses. And what reverence was done in such holy places, appears, both by the words of <hi>Jacob, How fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and dreadfull is this place;</hi> and by the command of God to <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Joshua,</hi> to <hi>put off their shoes;</hi> and by <hi>Davids</hi> speech, <hi>I will come into thy house in the multitude of thy mercies, and in thy fear will I worship towards this holy temple;</hi> and <hi>O come let us worship,</hi> &amp;c. And all this they did without any command from God, but from the light of nature,, and by the received rule and tradition of the Church in all ages. And the same after them did the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Christians: <hi>Salvian</hi> relates the manner of their ingress into the Church; <hi>We rush to the House of God, we prostrate our selves upon the ground;</hi> and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends them that did enter into the House of God <hi>sine ulla penitus reverentia sacri honoris;</hi> and in the same place complains, that less honour was shewed to the House of God, than to the house of a petty Judg: and <hi>Chrysostome</hi> saith, they enterd the Church <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bowing their heads:</hi> and <hi>Isiodore Hispalensis</hi> layes down this rule, That if any came late after Prayers were begun, <hi>adoret prius postea attendat.</hi> And it was the constant practise of the Christians to bow towards the East, for which they were calumniated as <hi>Adoratores Orientis,</hi> as worshippers of the East; And such as resorted to the Church of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> are said, <hi>Adorare ad limina Apostolorum.</hi> And with the same reverence did they go out of the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it is in the Liturgy of St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> in the very conclusion of it; after the same manner that the Jewes did at their departure out of the Temple, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199259:7"/>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.28. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 46.2. whose incurvation was the space saith <hi>Maymonides,</hi> while a man might say, <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> And certainly, as it is a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discention in God, to accept of the same expression of reverence which we give unto men, so it is a great neglect and contempt of God in us, if we will not give that unto him which we do give to our betters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> saith, We pray <hi>manibus expansis quia innocuis, capite nudo quia non erubescemus;</hi> and S. <hi>Basil</hi> gives this Testimony of <hi>Gregory Thaumaturgus,</hi> That he never <hi>covered his head in the Church;</hi> Why so? <hi>Because he was</hi> (saith he) a <hi>true Scholler of the Apostle,</hi> who tells us, <hi>that every</hi> MAN PRAYING OR PROPHESYING <hi>having his head covered, dishonoureth his head:</hi> And the man ought not to cover his head, inasmuch as he is the image and glory of God. But how different is this from our practise? How do men rush in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods House without any reverence, and are almost at the upper end, before they think of their Hats? How do they sit like Quakers with their Hats nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to their heads, while the Preacher is delivering to them Gods Message with his head uncovered: So that should a Turk or an Infidel come into our Churches, he would by our behaviour take this place for a Theater, where the poor Parson is brought in like <hi>Sampson,</hi> to make the Lords of the <hi>Philistins</hi> with their Hats on, some sport and pastime. Sure I am, most of our people carry themselves in the Church as if it were not Gods House, or as if the Master of the House, were from home, and come with boldness sufficient to the Throne of Grace: And no marvel, if they be so rude, when as the Minister himself hath no more respect of that sacred Table, then of a Dresser-board, but lets it be exposed to the Prophanation of Boyes, and the pollution of Dogs: But let all such Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy men lay to heart the saying of an Italian Bishop; <hi>God in that holy Table which he finds full of dust, doth write down the faults of the careless Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> I shall conclude this with the eighteenth Canon of our Church; to which I refer you, and of which I expect an account from you.</p>
            <p>And if Holiness become Gods House, much more doth it those living Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the PRIESTS themselves: Let me therefore call upon you to make it a time of restoring for that too; namely HOLINESS, <hi>and blamelesness in your lives and conversations:</hi> This should be wrirten in our foreheads, <hi>Be ye pure, ye that bear the vessels of the Lord:</hi> And why doest thou <hi>take my word into thy mouth</hi> (saith God) <hi>seeing thou hatest to be reformed.</hi> Disorderliness is a spot in any coat, but a stain in the linnen Ephod; <hi>Nugae in ore sacerdotum sunt blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae,</hi> Such as are but vain words in another mans mouth, are blasphemies in a Ministers: <hi>Praesulis vitium non quam optimum esse,</hi> Its vice enough in a Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, not to excell others in vertue, let us therefore labour to be such as <hi>Gerhard</hi> the Monk, of whom S. <hi>Bernard</hi> speaks, <hi>Non in maximis tantum sed in minimis maximus erat:</hi> Let us make good the proceeding of that old Argument, <hi>Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199259:8"/>est, non fallet;</hi> and let every Minister be like <hi>Jonah</hi> the son of <hi>Amittui,</hi> the sons of <hi>truth,</hi> as some are called the Sons of <hi>thunder:</hi> And if any faults be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected against us, it will be some part of satisfaction, if in humility we can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer as S. <hi>Austin</hi> did the Donatists, <hi>Possunt haec veraciter dici &amp; nostra &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra, quae si utrisque nostrum disputent, neque nostra, neque vestra sunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And one particular let me warn you of, not so to busie your selves about farming and grazing, and such worldly imployments; for though in the late hard and miserable times, the Clergy might be excused for making use of those thrifty sayings of the Jewish Rabbies; <hi>Quis legem aut discit, aut docet, si fari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na desit?</hi> and <hi>bona est doctrina legis cum via terrae:</hi> yet now that the Churches maintenance is restored, let them bid adieu to their Farms and Oxen, their <hi>oves &amp; boves,</hi> and addict themselves wholly to <hi>feed the flock of God commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their charge;</hi> Your title in Greek implys a contradiction to earthliness; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in that Language is all one as <hi>unearthly.</hi> And your name of <hi>Seers,</hi> intimates, that you are not to intangle your selves with worldly affairs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments; for though the hands and the feet may without any great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency be dealing in the dust, and padling in the dirt, yet the eye cannot without damage or danger admit ought of either. And indeed, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that great weight and charge laid upon you, you will find but little time for such <hi>Parerga</hi> and impertinencies: If God think it work enough for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel to keep one soul, how vigilant ought they to be, who have the charge of many. You are Intelligencers, your Parish is the Orbe wherein you should continually move; you are the Sentinels, your Parish is the Watch-tower, where you are constantly to stand upon your duty; you are Candles, your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish is the Candlestick wherein you are to shine as lights in the world; You are the Shepherds, your Parish is the Flock whom you are to feed, for whom you are to provide, of whom you are to take the oversight, to whom you ought to be an example, which you cannot well be unless you visit your people, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from house to house, and though the Church be your Center, yet your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish is to be your circumference.</p>
            <p>And now in the last place, If you would make the times of Restoring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; add one thing more, and that is the restoring of your PROCURATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS: Though thus long you have detained them, and none said, <hi>Restore,</hi> yet now I hope you will not stick at them any longer, considering that, <hi>Non remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, nisi restituatur;</hi> and that if you had sooner furnisht me with those neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary supplies, I had been restored to you the sooner.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:199259:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>